<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Digikata Blog</title>
    <subtitle>My underupdated blog</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://digikata.com/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://digikata.com/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Getting Started with Rust Tracing</title>
        <published>2025-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/getting-started-with-rust-tracing/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/getting-started-with-rust-tracing/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Tracing crate for Rust is a well-implemented tracing library for a wide
range of tracing and logging needs. However, I haven&#x27;t seen a simple startup
guide for tracing. This is what would have saved me some time when
getting started with Tracing. This goes over a very common setup of defining
a default set of trace levels, while accepting an overriding setup from
the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;RUST_LOG&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; environment variable. It will also go over tips on how
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;RUST_LOG&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; can be used. &lt;em&gt;(Learning to use &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;RUST_LOG&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; beyond the simple
setting of a global log level is worth it!)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Resource: Testing Distributed Systems</title>
        <published>2022-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2022-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/links-testing-distributed-sys/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/links-testing-distributed-sys/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A nice resource on testing distributed systems including approaches and public real world instances of projects tested.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On github &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;asatarin&#x2F;testing-distributed-systems&quot;&gt;~astarain&#x2F;testing-distributed-systems&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Article: A journey to io_uring, AIO and modern storage devices</title>
        <published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/article-modern-storage-devices/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/article-modern-storage-devices/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A nice article, with backing paper surveying a lot of interesting high-performance
characteristics of hard drives, SATA SSDs, NVMe SSDs, and Optane devices.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;clickhouse.tech&#x2F;blog&#x2F;en&#x2F;2021&#x2F;reading-from-external-memory&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Reading from External Memory&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paper below:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Rust and io_uring Part 1</title>
        <published>2020-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2020-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/rust-io-uring-part1/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/rust-io-uring-part1/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are really a lot of different io_uring crates for rust. Some are quick
bindings, some are specialized to particular application or runtime
environments, some are doing deeper experiments to how they connect to the
applications using the interface,  I think I&#x27;ll start looking at them to
contrast their approaches in a little more detail.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Paper: Erasure Coding for production in the EOS Open Storage system</title>
        <published>2020-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2020-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/erasure-coding-cern/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/erasure-coding-cern/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A paper on use of per-file Erasure Coding redundancy in the EOS Filesystem used at CERN. Reasonably basic use of EC at this level of description, but it is always nice to see a review of various design decisons in a real world system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract, comments and links further on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Blog Reboot</title>
        <published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/blog-reboot/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/blog-reboot/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Time to reboot my blog. The old &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;digikata.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;site&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is still
served by Blogger but, I will probably shift the content to this main site at
some point.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site is generated by the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.getzola.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Zola&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; static site
generator written in rust. Hosted on github static pages. See below the fold
for misc details.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Counteracting High Speed Traders</title>
        <published>2010-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2010-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2010-06-counteracting-high-speed-traders/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2010-06-counteracting-high-speed-traders/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2010-06-counteracting-high-speed-traders/">&lt;p&gt;On the Planet Money &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.npr.org&#x2F;blogs&#x2F;money&#x2F;&quot;&gt;show&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, there&#x27;s been discussion about the practice of High Speed Trading. This is where traders use computers and high-speed connections to the stock market to analyze trade data and put in trades making penny or sub-penny profits on transaction trends by responding faster than other players.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for example, if someone is trying to make a buy of stocks, and they can&#x27;t get them in one lot, their first partial buy might trigger an algorithm in a computer. Then the computer might use it&#x27;s high speed trading connection to buy up available lots of the stock that it anticipates will soon go up by a small tick, reselling to a slower moving buyer trying to close out the complete order with a slower connection.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Institutional investors, such as those managing your pension mutual funds, are understandably wary of the practice because they&#x27;re frequently the ones whose transactions become marginally more expensive due to high-speed trading algorithms. So how might they neutralize the effects of high-speed traders?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see an opening where a larger traders could help to neutralize or even marginally improve transaction costs due high-speed traders via counter trades.  In aircraft control theory, there is a phenomenon called &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Pilot-induced_oscillation&quot;&gt;pilot induced oscillation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (PIO). This is where a pilot tries to damp out an oscillation, but because they&#x27;re responding with the right response, but out of phase, the situation ends up inducing larger oscillations in the path of the aircraft. Usually, aircraft designers (and pilots) are looking to avoid PIO, but a counter trade would be trying for the opposite by inducing high speed trading responses.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic idea would be to issue a number of counter trades to trigger the high speed trading algorithms, then use the window of movement in price that the high-speed algorithm creates to run your intended overall transaction. For example, if you were selling, make a few buys first. Let the high speed algos try to drive the price up by buying up all the shares at that local price level, then you would issue your sale at a higher transaction price. If the high speed trading algorithms stay agressive, then you can continue to open windows for your intended transactions. Alternately if the high-speed algorithms are dialed down to become less aggressive then your marginal losses from the actions are drastically reduced. Either way, counter trading would be one way to bound the high-speed trading algorithms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: in the same vein, here&#x27;s an &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theatlantic.com&#x2F;science&#x2F;archive&#x2F;2010&#x2F;08&#x2F;market-data-firm-spots-the-tracks-of-bizarre-robot-traders&#x2F;60829&#x2F;&quot;&gt;article&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in the Atlantic about how odd trading patterns have been identified in trading data, presumeably from high frequency trading bots.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Phase Change Capsules in Drywall</title>
        <published>2010-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2010-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2010-02-phase-change-capsules-in-drywall/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2010-02-phase-change-capsules-in-drywall/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2010-02-phase-change-capsules-in-drywall/">&lt;p&gt;What a great &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.technologyreview.com&#x2F;energy&#x2F;24476&#x2F;?ref=rss&quot;&gt;idea&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Daytime heat is absorbed into little capsules of a material that changes phase. The material is mixed into drywall plaster. Rooms stay cool. At night the heat is released. Great primary function, but the material is made from a process that coats Paraffin wax. I have to wonder how that does for fire resistance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>iPad and Interface Single Tasking</title>
        <published>2010-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2010-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2010-01-ipad-and-interface-single-tasking/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2010-01-ipad-and-interface-single-tasking/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2010-01-ipad-and-interface-single-tasking/">&lt;p&gt;Geeks of the world went through a collective wave of anticipation and lament yesterday at the unveling of the Apple &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.apple.com&#x2F;ipad&#x2F;&quot;&gt;iPad&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.  If there was a single most missed feature, it was probably the lack of multitasking. I&#x27;m going to say something contrarian here.  The iPad doesn&#x27;t need multitasking now, and possibly not ever.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the iPad, Apple is taking a step down the path where separation between interface and application (or Model from the View and Controller if you prefer) is not just a convenient software architecture boundary, but is an actual physical interface boundary. As much as you might wish it, humans are, at best, serial-taskers when it comes to interfacing to a computer system. Notice I said system. The next logical step after the iPad is to seamlessly connect it to other higher horsepower devices; devices on the net, or devices in a cloud. Personally, the link net devices are fairly mature over the browser, but I&#x27;d like to start maturing the link to my personal, home computing devices, the cloud can come later.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the iPad is just an interface device with just enough computing power to ease local controls processing, you can then multitask to your hearts desire by giving server type devices tasks to go off and perform. Basically, as long as you can push images onto the iPad  and control commands back to a server, and do lightweight processing for compromises between those two extremes, you can think of the iPad as a physical manifestation of a application gui window on your desktop computer.
The only thing you need is a multi-event notification system, which iPhone already has a least laid a foundation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some short-term, established ways to pursue this link, the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;X_Window_System&quot;&gt;X window system&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a prime example. For more recent examples, you could look at VNC&#x2F;Remote Desktops type applications to extend your interface device. Ironically, the VNC&#x2F;Remote desktop applications are less rich than the X system. And of course, browsers are increasingly delivering reasonably responsive application over web technologies. This should only get easier with the rise of HTML5. However, Apple has always dabbled in interesting interface and display technologies. I&#x27;m hoping that Apple has it&#x27;s sights set on a longer term view of this path and is preparing some newly rethought method of linking server side power to an exportable iPad interface that may blow the doors off of all these paradigms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Healthcare Soda: Predictably Broken Competitive Markets</title>
        <published>2009-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2009-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2009-08-healthcare-soda-predictably-broken-competitive-mar/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2009-08-healthcare-soda-predictably-broken-competitive-mar/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2009-08-healthcare-soda-predictably-broken-competitive-mar/">&lt;p&gt;Interesting data on health care by &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;blogs.harvardbusiness.org&#x2F;haque&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Umair Haque&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; at the Harvard Business Review in &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;blogs.harvardbusiness.org&#x2F;haque&#x2F;2009&#x2F;08&#x2F;how_to_think_constructively_ab.html&quot;&gt;this article&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. (he actually has a lot of interesting articles in HBR.) I&#x27;ve been thinking that the private healthcare industry as a competitive market is pretty broken in the US. It&#x27;s not really surprising to me that a competitive market works very poorly with its characteristics. For a market to work best, a purchase should have verifiable quality and needs to be repeatable or reversible, meaning you make that purchase decision again and again, or if you find a choice was bad, you can change the choice or reverse it.  For example, that may mean giving back the product, or discarding it for another, or selling to someone else. Here&#x27;s an example:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you buy a soda, then take a sip, and find that you hate the taste. No big deal - if its really that bad, you could stop drinking it partway through and toss it. Choose another brand next time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Healthcare doesn&#x27;t work that way. Now imagine if the only way to shop for soda is to buy a can every month and put it in the garage. If you open that soda you have to keep that can, finish the drink, finish what&#x27;s in the garage, and keep buying it for a while. That&#x27;s what happens if you get seriously ill and really need to lean on that health insurance. You might know how an insurer handles routine care, but you really don&#x27;t know the quality of your health provider until you&#x27;re in dire straits. At that point, you can&#x27;t switch.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these circumstances, is it any wonder that there is a fundamental disconnect between the profit of health insurance companies they quality they deliver. In California, there&#x27;s been an ongoing fight about insurance companies cancelling policies when when serious care is needed (search for &quot;California lawsuit health insurance cancellation&quot; or click &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;&#x2F;www.google.com&#x2F;search?hl=en&amp;amp;q=california+health+insurance+cancellation+lawsuits&quot;&gt;here.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; Some of  insurance companies even paid employees bonuses to cancel policies of very sick people based on technicalities on their initial applications (sometimes years back).  Settlements in some of those cases after the fact must be very bittersweet I&#x27;m sure that some of those patients received worse care, or suffered permanent injury or death.  Finally, if you can&#x27;t work, eventually you hit the end of what you&#x27;re employer is willing and able to provide and you go bankrupt. This drives a suprisingly large portion of bankruptcies in the United States (article &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.forbes.com&#x2F;feeds&#x2F;hscout&#x2F;2009&#x2F;06&#x2F;04&#x2F;hscout627785.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&#x27;t even touched upon how things  are even more broken because we&#x27;re not even the ones shopping for this healthcare soda. Our employers are usually the one shopping for it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t know how to fix things - I do like to idea of a publicly chartered competitor to private insurance, but really we need to find a way to connect up the healthcare market costs to delivered value to us, the consumers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Touchable Holograms</title>
        <published>2009-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2009-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2009-08-touchable-holograms/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2009-08-touchable-holograms/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2009-08-touchable-holograms/">&lt;p&gt;Popular Science posted this &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.popsci.com&#x2F;entertainment-amp-gaming&#x2F;article&#x2F;2009-08&#x2F;tokyo-scientists-create-touchable-hologram&quot;&gt;article&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and video about touchable holograms at &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.siggraph.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Siggraph&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &#x27;09, this year. It&#x27;s a combination of three items: a 3d display using concave mirrors something like this &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.amazon.com&#x2F;Toysmith-79747-Mini-3-D-Mirascope&#x2F;dp&#x2F;B000N5T8KA&quot;&gt;3D mirascope toy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, two wii-motes strapped statically for position detection, and a home-brewed (university-brewed?) &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Phased_array&quot;&gt;phased array&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; of ultrasound drivers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>A Sheeva Plug Computer would make a great NAS</title>
        <published>2009-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2009-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2009-03-a-sheeva-plug-computer-would-make-a-great-nas/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2009-03-a-sheeva-plug-computer-would-make-a-great-nas/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2009-03-a-sheeva-plug-computer-would-make-a-great-nas/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;&#x2F;4.bp.blogspot.com&#x2F;_kAb6SmYM0ko&#x2F;ScmySUL7TlI&#x2F;AAAAAAAAADA&#x2F;3AEnp1PAq48&#x2F;s1600-h&#x2F;sheevaplug.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;&#x2F;4.bp.blogspot.com&#x2F;_kAb6SmYM0ko&#x2F;ScmySUL7TlI&#x2F;AAAAAAAAADA&#x2F;3AEnp1PAq48&#x2F;s320&#x2F;sheevaplug.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
I&#x27;ve been looking at the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.marvell.com&#x2F;products&#x2F;embedded_processors&#x2F;developer&#x2F;kirkwood&#x2F;sheevaplug.jsp&quot;&gt;Sheeva Plug dev kit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; from Marvell. It seems to be an ARM core System-on-Chip (SoC), Linux compatible, with an interesting combo of device controllers hanging off of it, including ethernet, USB, and SATA ports.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dev kit seems to be the size of a large wall wart and part of Marvell&#x27;s &quot;Plug Computing&quot; marketing drive. Not sure about plug computing bit, but I&#x27;d love to fit the board into a small two or three bay external drive enclosure, or maybe a drive &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.geeks.com&#x2F;details.asp?invtid=EN391&amp;amp;cat=CSE&quot;&gt;dock&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.  Running a minimal linux system, a looks like it would be a nice way to setup a local Network Attached Storage (NAS) backup system with enough smarts to do offsite backups to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;aws.amazon.com&#x2F;s3&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Amazon S3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or Rackspace&#x27;s &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.mosso.com&#x2F;cloudfiles.jsp&quot;&gt;Mosso&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Telephones over the Internet, a Skype vs Gizmo5 comparison</title>
        <published>2009-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2009-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2009-02-telephones-over-the-internet-a-skype-vs-gizmo5-com/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2009-02-telephones-over-the-internet-a-skype-vs-gizmo5-com/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2009-02-telephones-over-the-internet-a-skype-vs-gizmo5-com/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.flickr.com&#x2F;photos&#x2F;adselwood&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;&#x2F;4.bp.blogspot.com&#x2F;_kAb6SmYM0ko&#x2F;SbmtOR0_L0I&#x2F;AAAAAAAAAC4&#x2F;ZoiZC2HYmhM&#x2F;s200&#x2F;network-tangle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
Engineers are always trying to optimize value - sometime&#x27;s we choose the wrong values to optimize on, but thats a discussion for another day. Recently, I&#x27;ve been looking through different VoIP services to see how viable they are as ways of augmenting or replacing my residential land-line phone service. VoIP is Voice over Internet Protocol. The per-minute prices for VoIP are free-to-low, with direct computer-to-computer calls typically free and computer-to-phone service typically at a low monthly or per-minute fee.  A computer-to-phone call is often called PSTN or Public Switch Telephone Network termination. There are also other variations on this where you call and the service calls back but, for me, those services are more hassle than they&#x27;re worth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VoIP phoning isn&#x27;t as reliable as regular landline phones. e.g. in a power outage, you have to have your own backup to run the computer or other devices needed to connect to the internet -- and even that is futile if you net connection goes down with the power. Between the power and issues about getting correct 911 service, etc, VoIP is something I see as a way to augment my current service by reducing cost for non-emergency calls.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, after looking through a number of different options, &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;skype.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Skype&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;gizmo5.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Gizmo5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; are two services of interest. They break up their costs in different ways, and there are various technical and market aspects that might make one favor one vs another. For example, I like that Gizmo5 uses standard communication protocols to initiate and transfer calls while Skype uses more proprietary methods. They also both offer other services that I wouldn&#x27;t use very often, such as video chat.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, one thing that both work with is my Ipod Touch 2G. An Ipod application called &quot;Fring&quot; allows calls over WiFi using a number of VoIP services. It&#x27;s a geeky feature to play with but there constraints there that make me think that this won&#x27;t be the way I put the most hours on a VoIP service. More on that later maybe, but I&#x27;ll just close out talk of Fring with the statement that it&#x27;s use of standard protocols such as a SIP VoIP interface is what allows Gizmo5 to work with Fring. This is one reason to like standards&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, both offer service-to-service calls for free. So really I&#x27;m comparing the cost of making computer to phone calls. Gizmo5 offers bridging calls to Skype for a flat fee for time. This seems somewhat unreliable, presumably because Skype doesn&#x27;t encourage this. Skype has a larger user base, but is owned by questionably consumer friendly Ebay (also owner of PayPal).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of flat rate service, Gizmo5 offers 1.9 ct&#x2F;min rates while Skypes are 2.1ct&#x2F;min. Skype also charges a connection fee of 3.5 cents. So for flat rate service Skype loses out pricewise. Skype, however, also offers unlimited calls for $2.95&#x2F;mo. So the breakpoint is ~155minutes for Gizmo5 vs skype. Meaning if you plan to consistently use more than 155 minutes a month on a service like this then Skype will be cheaper. Since this is an addon side service, I think I&#x27;m going with Gizmo5 - I liked their use of open connection protocols anyway.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I first wrote this post the LA Times ran an &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.latimes.com&#x2F;business&#x2F;la-fi-lazarus8-2009mar08,0,4417313.column&quot;&gt;article&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; on a study citing the average cost that consumers pay for cellular service -- over $3 per minute wow...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(photo by: &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.flickr.com&#x2F;photos&#x2F;adselwood&#x2F;&quot;&gt;asdelwood&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, under a &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;creativecommons.org&#x2F;licenses&#x2F;by&#x2F;2.0&#x2F;deed.en&quot;&gt;Creative Commons&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; license on &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.flickr.com&#x2F;photos&#x2F;adselwood&#x2F;2594981946&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Flickr&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>ATT U-Verse vs. ?</title>
        <published>2009-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2009-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2009-02-att-u-verse-vs/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2009-02-att-u-verse-vs/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2009-02-att-u-verse-vs/">&lt;p&gt;About a year ago ATT started rolling out U-Verse in my neighborhood. Since then, every quarter or so, I get an ATT marketing visitor to my door trying to sell me the service which is, at its full glory,  a combined phone-internet-cable service. (and I think, is fiber-optic to some sort of neighborhood box, but not to your house). Today was the latest visit, but the first marketer was the worst, they didn&#x27;t know any details about the service except is fiber-optic and really great. They didn&#x27;t know what channels they deliver, they didn&#x27;t know the up and down speeds of the net connection, they didn&#x27;t know the price of the accounts after the &quot;promotional period&quot; was over. Somehow they were trained to expect such exitement over the phrase &quot;fiber-optic&quot; that they could instantly sell the new U-Verse service. Oh, that and combined billing. I really really don&#x27;t care about combined billing. I care about what I actually get for my money.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, things have improved a little. At least the reps know the very basic details of whats offered, like what is the actual speed of the network link that I get. Still when the ATT rep shows up at my door again, and we talk about the detals beyond &quot;its fiber-optic and it&#x27;s great&quot;, I find again and again that for the services that I care about - all three categories are more expensive then my current services. Maybe I&#x27;m just an uber-consumer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, I think the fundamental problem is that ATT doesn&#x27;t understand that I&#x27;m a telecom Luddite. My landline service is basic with no additional phone services like caller ID, etc. My cell phone is pay-as-you-go.  Between the barebones local-only ATT account and my third-party long distance company, my family and I make basically unlimited calls for a combined 20-35 a month.  The ATT price would be $30&#x2F;mo. I only very occasionally break $30 a month so really ATT loses here.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My net connection is a third-party DSL provider at $20&#x2F;mo for 3Mbps down and 768kbs up. ATT&#x27;s rep today claimed 3Mbps  down and 1 Mbps up (their website claims  512bps up) for $30&#x2F;month, or for $20&#x2F;month I can get 768&#x2F;384 kbps. Either again the shiny fiber-optic almost-to-the-home service loses again. The ironic thing here is that ATT supplies the underlying DSL connection here either way, but can&#x27;t seem to keep from offering pathetic value for internet connections.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I&#x27;m also a cable Luddite. Dish Network charges about $35&#x2F;mo for local channels and a number of basic cable channels. It&#x27;s pointless comparing the actual number of channels between a given ATT and Dish plan because it would inevitably end up with a race bewteen who offers more QVC or Jewelry TV shopping channels. ATT&#x27;s U-Verse service starts at $54 a month. My family already watches as much programming as they have time for, and with a Netflix account, we what whatever piques our interest. Maybe that makes my family post-telecom consumers or something like that. I value the Netflix service more than I value a higher tier cable service, but if I added that cost in, ATT would come in at $4&#x2F;mo higher.  Still U-Verses loses again to the tune of $4 to $20 a month.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for me, U-Verse offers no reason to pay more per month for about the same service. Maybe U-Verse offers some value to people paying for more premium services that I care to get, but until ATT offers some better value to this customer --  well, I guess I&#x27;ll see them in three months.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Etch-A-Sketch Patent</title>
        <published>2009-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2009-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2009-02-etch-a-sketch-patent/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2009-02-etch-a-sketch-patent/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2009-02-etch-a-sketch-patent/">&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;digikata.com&#x2F;2009-02-etch-a-sketch-patent&#x2F;www.google.com&#x2F;patents?id=ODpuAAAAEBAJ&amp;amp;dq=3055113&quot;&gt;link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to the patent for Etch-a-Sketch - originally called the GrandJean Tracing Device on Google Patents.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Olympics Siverlight missing?</title>
        <published>2008-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2008-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2008-11-olympics-siverlight-missing/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2008-11-olympics-siverlight-missing/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2008-11-olympics-siverlight-missing/">&lt;p&gt;Hmm, cleaning out my bookmarks, I opened up the NBC Olympics site. At the height of the 2008 Olympics they had been running Microsoft&#x27;s &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;silverlight.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Silverlight&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; pretty heavily all over the place. Today, because I run &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;noscript.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;NoScript&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; on Firefox, I see a big pre-loading box saying - download Adobe flash 7 or higher all over the place. The videos still seem to use silverlight though... Ah I&#x27;m probably just remembering wrong.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Sun Images</title>
        <published>2008-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2008-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2008-11-sun-images/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2008-11-sun-images/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2008-11-sun-images/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.boston.com&#x2F;bigpicture&#x2F;2008&#x2F;10&#x2F;the_sun.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;&#x2F;3.bp.blogspot.com&#x2F;_kAb6SmYM0ko&#x2F;SSOtKwAWD_I&#x2F;AAAAAAAAACw&#x2F;ubngh__1Vt8&#x2F;s200&#x2F;sunpic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;I love &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.boston.com&#x2F;bigpicture&#x2F;2008&#x2F;10&#x2F;the_sun.html&quot;&gt;these&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; solar images. Nature is beautiful. #9 is one of my favorites. Once you&#x27;re through with looking at the sun imagery, look at some of the other &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.boston.com&#x2F;bigpicture&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Big Picture&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; columns. Who says that newspapers can&#x27;t figure out the web. The &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.boston.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Boston Globe&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; seems to be doing well in the medium in this case.
(from &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;digg.com&#x2F;space&#x2F;Incredible_Images_of_the_Sun_PICS&quot;&gt;Digg&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Bailout Opinion</title>
        <published>2008-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2008-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2008-11-bailout-opinion/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2008-11-bailout-opinion/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2008-11-bailout-opinion/">&lt;p&gt;Not that it would ever happen, but I think that if the taxpayers are bailing out the Big 3 automakers, we should basically require them to be broken up into smaller independent companies.  Down the line, if they waste the opportunity (ahem Chrysler), then at that point, they should be small enough to fail and would be replaced by healthier, more responsive companies that can restart from a fresh perspective -- like &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.aptera.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Aptera&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.teslamotors.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Tesla&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.wrightspeed.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Wrightspeed&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (and those are just the exciting ones there are more boring competitors...).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Lego Sifting Box</title>
        <published>2008-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2008-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2008-10-lego-sifting-box/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2008-10-lego-sifting-box/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2008-10-lego-sifting-box/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.box4blox.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;&#x2F;1.bp.blogspot.com&#x2F;_kAb6SmYM0ko&#x2F;SPbG_8GZFNI&#x2F;AAAAAAAAACo&#x2F;Tew9AQMC3H8&#x2F;s200&#x2F;box4blox-cross-section.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
I recently purchased a Lego organizing case for my son called &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.box4blox.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Box4Blox&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It was a little overpriced if one was comparing cost at the material level, but it had a great feature of being able to sift and grade Lego parts. The item has four trays with different sized gridded grilles underneath three of them. From top to bottom, the grills get increasingly smaller, sifting out larger Lego pieces and letting the smaller ones fall through. My only complaint is that the box wasn&#x27;t larger for the price. Once a tray gets about 60% full, the &quot;sifting-action&quot; gets a little choked out. Overall the Box4Blox sifter is a great product. My son happily found a renewed interest in his Lego toys as soon as he was able to get to a wider array of different types and sizes of parts easily.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>U.S. Farmers Save By Installing Manure Digesters</title>
        <published>2008-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2008-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://digikata.com/2008-10-us-farmers-save-by-installing-manure-digesters/"/>
        <id>https://digikata.com/2008-10-us-farmers-save-by-installing-manure-digesters/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://digikata.com/2008-10-us-farmers-save-by-installing-manure-digesters/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.flickr.com&#x2F;photos&#x2F;foxypar4&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;&#x2F;3.bp.blogspot.com&#x2F;_kAb6SmYM0ko&#x2F;SOfLS-xa2KI&#x2F;AAAAAAAAACg&#x2F;JoUAtssdd2A&#x2F;s320&#x2F;924981320_f1e688b289_m.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
Popular Mechanics has posted an &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.popularmechanics.com&#x2F;science&#x2F;earth&#x2F;4285577.html?nav=rss20&quot;&gt;article&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; interviewing dairy farmer Shawn Saylor. Saylor describes the multiple benefits of the anarobic biodigester system he installed. I&#x27;ve always thought that there was an archetype of a small, savvy, independent citizen-farmer at the heart of the image of a pragmatic can-do attitude of America. It&#x27;s great to see that showing in the article.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The digester system is fundamentally improving Saylor&#x27;s bottom line dairy finances while providing a number of side benefits.  For example, on the finance side, the digester provides electric, heat, and fertilizer.  It makes him money by offsetting his electric bill, fuel for heat, in addition to putting electric back into the grid. Incidentally, it also reduces the dairy manure waste stream into the watershed while also diverting a lot of gases which would otherwise enter the atmosphere driving global climate change. I am speculating a little here on the overall benefit - the gases are still burnt, generating carbon dioxide, but I&#x27;m guessing that&#x27;s less harmful that methane going directly into the atmosphere. The electricity put back into the grid would offset other carbon sources that would have been used anyway for the farm and his neighbors...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This installation was helped by a government grant partially offsetting the cost of the system. To me this is a great example of how government should be involved in accelerating common sense green technologies. Or in economic terms, reducing the cost of social externalities while improving the efficiency of businesses. The cost of the grant is offset by the long term efficiency in the dairy business which benefits the government in improved long term tax base.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.popularmechanics.com&#x2F;science&#x2F;earth&#x2F;4285577.html?nav=rss20&quot;&gt;article&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; from Popular Mechanics, Creative Commons photo from Flickr user &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.flickr.com&#x2F;people&#x2F;foxypar4&#x2F;&quot;&gt;foxypar4&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
